Guide to the Arthur L. Bloom papers, 1960-1971.
Bloom, Arthur L. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Arthur L. Bloom papers, 1960-1971.
16-14-4167
Arthur L. (Arthur Leroy), Bloom, 1928-
.1 cubic feet.
Slides, correspondence, research materials, reports, publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files relating to the Cornell Geology Department, especially department meetings and curriculum changes.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor Emeritus, Earth and Atmospheric Sciences.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files relating to the Cornell Geology Department, especially department meetings and curriculum changes.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bloom, Arthur L. (Arthur Leroy), (Arthur Leroy), 1928-; Cornell University. Department of Geology; Cornell University -- Faculty.
Subjects:
Geology -- Study and teaching.; Geologists.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Slides
Series II. Research Materials and Publications
Series III. Career, Public Outreach, Personal
Series IV. Geology administrative documents
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Slides
  - Subseries Ia. USA, Jamaica, Bermuda, Barbados
    - 1987 Campus PR, Expression (Box 2, Folder 1)
      photo slides of Cornell's campus
    - Connecticut salt marshes: lecture, 1972-03-22-1976-10-12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Connecticut salt marshes: lecture
    - Connecticut coast 1960-62, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      lecture notes and slides
    - Connecticut coast 1963-64, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Connecticut coast, 1965-78 + etc., 1965-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Maine-New Hampshire-Vermont (less Isles of Shoals), 1958-2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      email and written correspondence; photo slides
    - Mt. Washington, New Hampshire, 1953-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Southeastern US coast, 1959-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Appalachians - Stroudsburg FOTP, N.J., Va, We Va. avalanches; air views, 1961-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Eastward cruise, 1970, southeast. US shelf, 1970-03-1970-04 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Florida Everglads and Miami, 1964-11-1981-06 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Gulf Coast, La., E Texas, 1959-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Eastward Cruise, 1973; Jamaica, 1973-03 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Bermuda - April 1987, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Barbados, 1972, 1972-06 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Canada - Maritimes; Banff, Alberta; Onatrio, Quebec, 1962-1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Periglacial Alaska, Greenland, Canada, 1958-1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Geological Survey of Americ (GSA) field trips, Cincinnati and Milwaukee, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Sierra Madre field camp '83, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - International Geoscience Programme (INQUA) 1965, Trip E, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Paradox Basin, June 1980, 1976-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Asst. Western trips: Colorado, Wyoming, Ariz., 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Permian Basin - West Texas, New Mexico, 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Penrose Tectonic Geomorph '83; Bull, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Aerial Views, Western U.S., 1967-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Death Valley; JPL Radar May 1 '86, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - California Coast. 1978, 1979 (Ventura, Geological Survey of America), 1954-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mono Basin, CA, 1965-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      correspondence, prints, The Mono Lake Newsletter Spring 1992, notes, photo slides
    - Seattle, Cascades (+purchased) 1975, 1972-1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries Ib. Brazil, Argentina, and Peru
    - Miscell. Graphics, A - International Geoscience Programme (IGCP), 1967-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      subfolder entitled "NASA Site Visit and notes"
    - Isostasy, etc. (including Preuss and Clark), 1956-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Andes - SX lecture set, 1983-1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Argentina: Landsat, block diagonal; graphics, 1972-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Punta Negra
    - TM scenes: graphics, closeups, etc., 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Ollague/S. Puna volcanoes, 1984-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - West Quilmes: TM, aerial, ground, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ancasti Ranges: TM, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Mendoza, Aconcagua, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sras. Cordoba; Sra Grande; Chica, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Chepes/Ulapes - Las Minas, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Landsat MSS black and white, central Andes + TJ slides, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Pie de Palo: LFC, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Duplicates of Bossi sets - Apr/May 86, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Sta Barbara E of Salta; TM 230-78-1-5.4.2, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Argentina slides April 1982, 1982-04 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Argentina, March and April '82, 1982-03-1982-04 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Argentina, June 1983 - Folder 1, 1983-06 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Argentina, June 1983 - Folder 2, 1983-06 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Argentina 1984 Rolls 1-11 Rolls; Max. del P. - Bariloche - BA, 1984-10 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Argentina 1984 Rolls 12-17 - Ba/Santa Maria/Cordoba, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Includes Oct 20-26, 1984 field notes and photo log
    - Argentina 1984 rolls 18-22 + N2/N4; Rio Pico/Bariloche, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Argentina - Sir - B/Rio Pico, 1984-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Photo slides 1984; correspondence 2004
    - Argentina, Jan '86: 25°-42°, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Argentina, 1990, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Peru, Sept. 1984 (rolls 1-6-25 + N-1), 1981-2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      photo slides; printed diagrams
    - Peru, 1985 (Marcona --> Ilo), 1985-06-1985-07 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Brazil 1978, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Bank note from Brazil; field book 1978; Sao Paulo city guide; tourist pamphlets; photo slides
  - Subseries Ic. Southwest Pacific, New Zealand, and Australia
    - SX - Ice ages, S. Pacific, 1972-1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      lecture notes; photo slides
    - Tonga, 1974 - 1978, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Fiji, 1951-1976 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - New Caledonia, 1974 + 1976, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Carmarsel 1967-1968, Rolls 1-4, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Carmarsel, 1967, Rolls 5-9, 1967-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Carmarsel, 1967, Rolls 10-14, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - New Zealand, 1973 - 1974, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - North Q'land; Townsville '73, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Australia 1952, 1976, 1978, 1952-2010 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Townsville, Q'land 1973 - Air Views, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Gt. Barrier Reef, 1973, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Sydney, Canberra, Tas., 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - New Guinea, 1971, Rolls 1-3, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - New Guinea, 1971, Rolls 4-7, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - New Guinea, 1971, Rolls 8-10, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - New Guinea 1973 Inqua-Huon, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - New Guinea Inqua trip, 1973 - Highlands, 1973-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Efate 1974, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Western Samoa, 1974, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - New Hebrides 1976, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - New Hebrides 1978, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Vanuatu 1979, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Vanuatu 1981, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Huon Peninsula, PNG, 1982-2000 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Hawaii, 1974 (+1951, 1953), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hawaii and Maui, 1975 and 1979, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Kauai, Hawaii, 1980-1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      photo slides; 1995 newspaper article regarding Hawaii Volcano National Park
    - Nauru-Ponape 1981, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      contains map and articles about Nauru
    - Guam-- Rota and Saipan, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Subseries Id. Japan, Korea, China
    - US Navy West Pacific 1953-1954, 1953-1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Japan 1978 + 1975 w/Jakarta, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Japan 1980 Rolls 1-9; Hakone, Rokko, I3u, Hiroshima, Nagoya, Shikoku, Sado, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Japan 1980, Rolls 10-14; Sadois, Toyama, Kanazawa, Kobe, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Japan 1980, Rolls 15-19; Ryukyu Is. start. Aso volc., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Japan 1980 Rolls 20-26; Aso volc., Kyushu, Kobe Harbor, Kyoto, Tokyo, Nikko, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Japan 1981 - 1990, 1981-1990 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Japan 1988 - 1994, 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Korea 1978, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - China Sept '82 (1-5), 1982 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - China Sept '82 (6-10), 1982 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Subseries Ie. Europe, USSR, Saudi Arabia, Dakan
    - Sweden and Gt. Britain, 1977 - 1992, 1977-1992 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      photo slides, 1992 academic paper
    - Europe: International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA), 1969 + etc., 1948-1969 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      photo slides, annotated International Union for Quaternary (INQUA) Research Atlantic Coast 1969 publication
    - Neoglaciation: esp. Rhone Glacier, 1976-1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      photo slides, correspondence, publications
    - Netherlands International Geoscience Programme (IGCP), 1974, 1974-1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Italy 1953 - Jan 1983, 1953-1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Greece, Jan. 1984, 1984-01 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Santorini/Thera, 1986-2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Academic publication concerning dendrochronology and ice core analysis with primary focus on Santorini eruption; Santorini tour pamphlet
    - Spain - Grenada, Toledo, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - USSR - International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA), 1965-1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      photo slides, field notes
    - Saudi Arabia January 1983, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Dakar International Geoscience Programme (IGCP), + Morroco Tour Dec. 1976, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Series II. Research Materials and Publications
  - Yale notes and photos, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Lit. cited and suggestions for further reading, 1968-08-06-1968-09-09 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Japanese edition, Surface of the Earth, 1969-07-26-1970-07-04 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Recent crustal movement Global Survey of Canada (GSC), 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Eustatic isotosy, 1964-1967 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Encyclopedia America 197 - Fingerlakes, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Bloom 1963 American Journal of Science - Late Pleistocene - movements in Maine, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Bloom American Journal of Science 1963, 1963-1971 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Thesis source material, 1957-1962 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Bloom, 1967 Geological Survey of America Bulletin (GSAB). Pleistocene shorelines: a new test of isostasy, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Geological Survey of America (GSA) Guidebook - Paludal morphology, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bloom and Stuiver, 1963 Science, volume 139, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cline and Bloom 1965, Soil Survey of Cornell University property and associated areas east of the Cornell campus: Cornell Plantations, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bloom 1964. Peat accumulation and compaction in a Connecticut coastal marsh: Journal of Sedimentary Petrology. September 1964., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bloom 1963. The Explanatory Description of Coats., 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bloom 1965; Explanatory description of coasts: Zeitschrift für Geomorphologie, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sebago Lake State Park, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Office of Naval Research (ONR) - Reports, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Office of Naval Research (ONR) final report - requests, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Thesis photos, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Maine diagrams and figures, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The geology of Sebago Lake State Park: Maine Geological Survey, State Park Geological Series No 1, Augusta, Department of Economic Development, 24 p., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Maine Geological Survey - Late Pleistocene Changes of Sea Level in Southwestern Maine, 1960-10-01 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Submergence of the Connecticut coast: Science, v. 139, p. 332-334, 1963-01-25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Peat accumulation and compaction in a Connecticut coastal marsh: Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, v. 34, p. 599-603, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - A Hypothesis to Explain Pleistocene Climatic Fluctuations; Bloom/Orville; criticisms from reviewers, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Postglacial stratigraphy and morphology of Coastal Connecticut: Guidebook, Field Trip no. 5, Geological Society America Annual Meeting, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Soil survey of Cornell University property and associated areas east of the Cornell campus: Cornell Miscellaneous Bulletin 68, New York State College of Agriculture, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The explanatory desription of coasts: Zeitschrift für Geomorphologie, v. 9, p. 422-436, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Coastal geomorphology of Connecticut: Final Report, Office of Naval Research Project, 1967-2014 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Holocene changes in sea level: evidence in Micronesia: Science, v. 157, p. 542-544., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Surface of the Earth: Prentice-Hall, Inc., Englewood Cliffs, N.J., 152 p. (with translations in Japanese, 1969; Poruguese, 1970; Spanish, 1970; German, 1976; Polish, 1980) Reviews, 1969-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Paludal stratigraphy of Truk, Ponape, and Kusaie, Eastern Caroline Islands: Geological Society of America Bulletin., v. 81, p. 1895-1904., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Holocene submergence in Micronesia as the standard for eustatic sea-level changes: Quaternaria, v. 12, p. 145-154., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Glacial-eustatic and isostatic controls of sea level since the last glaciation, in Turekian, K.K., ed., Late Cenozoic Glacial Ages: Yale University Press, New Haven, p. 335-379., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Holocene sea-level changes, in Meyerson, A.L., and Zois, C.S., editors, Papers in Marine Science: The Link Lecture Series., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Geomorphology of reef complexes, in Laporte, L.Fl, editor., Reefs in time and space: Society of Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sir Charles Cotton: An appreciation, in Bold Coasts: Annotated reprints of selected papers on coastal geomorphology, 1916-1969; Cotton, C.A., (ed. B.W. Collins): A.H. and A.W. Reed, Wellington, N.Z., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Quaternary sea level fluctuations on a tectonic coast, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Sea-level movements during the last deglacial hemicycle (about 15,000 years):, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Taylor, F.W. and Bloom, A.L., Coral reefs on tectonic blocks, Tonga Island Arc: Third International Coral Reef Symposium, Miami, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Harrison, E.Z. and Bloom, A.L., Sedimentation rates on tidal salt marshes in Connecticut: Journal of Sedimentary Petrology, v. 47, p. 1484-1490., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bloom, A.L., Jouannic, C., and Taylor, F.W., Preliminary radiometric ages from the uplifted Quaternary coral reefs of Efate, in Ash, R.P., Carney, J.N., and Macfarlane, A., Geology of Efate and offshore islands: New Hebrides Condominium Geological Survey Regional Report, p. 47-49., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clark, J.A., and Bloom, A.L., Hydro-isotasy and Holocene emergence of South America in 1978 International Symposium on Coastal Evolution in the Quaternary, Sao Paulo, Brazil, Proceedings, p. 41-60., 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Clark and Bloom notes and acetates, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Oceans, Rivers, and Glaciers: The Geologic Story of the Finger Lakes Region, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - CARMARSEL - Geological Society of America (GSA), 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - New Orleans - Geological Society of America (GSA), 1967 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Shephard and others 1967, Holocene changes in sea level: evidence in Micronesia: Science v. 157 (no. 3778, 4 Aug), p. 542-544. Manuscripts. Edited file copy., 1967 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - National Science Foundation - West Pacific, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Notes: Micronesia, Bikini, Geological Society of America (GSA), 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - CARMARSEL peat and mud sample, radiocarbon for dating and description, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Shephard - Geological Society of America (GSA); CARMARSEL, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Paludal stratigraphy of Truk, Ponape, and Kusaie, Eastern Caroline Islands manuscript. Geological Society of America (GSA), 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Newell and Bloom - Geological Society of America Bulletin (GSA), 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - CARMARSEL; Curray and Shepard and Veeh, 1970, GSA, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists and Society for Sedimentary Geology: Symposium, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Society for Sedimentary Geology (SEPM); Reef geomorphology, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Society for Sedimentary Geology (SEPM); Manuscript (Geomorphology of Reef Complexes) and lecture notes, 1970-1974 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Panama, Mangrove Project, 1968-1971 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - American Quaternary Association (AMQUA) 1972, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Engineering Quarterly summer 1973, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Dr. T. Arihi, 1968-1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bishop, William W., 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Clayton correspondence, 1965-1972 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Contributions to Volumes I and II, Late-Quaternary Environments of the United States - Sea Level and Coastal Morphology of the United States through the Late Wisconsin Glacial Maximum; Sea Level and Coastal Changes, 1979-1983 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Flint Festschrift - Notes and Drafts, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Yale - Flint Festschrift, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Glacial-Eustatic and Isostatic Controls of Sea Level Since the Last Glaciation -- Yale Press 1971 2nd Draft, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA) -- Dipsticks, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Bloom 1969 - International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA) UNESCO (original manuscript), 1969 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA) 1969 - Paris, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - International Union for Quaternary Research (INQUA) 1973 Abstract, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Huon Penninsula manuscript - 2 drafts, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Atlas of Sea-Level Curves, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Extending the radiocarbon calibration beyond 26,000 years before present using fossil corals, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Radiocarbon calibration curve spanning 0 to 50,000 years BP based on 230Th/234U/238U and 14C dates on pristine corals, 2005-07-12 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Journal of Geography 1994 Snowline Altitude and Climate in the Peruvian Andes at Present and during the Latest Pleistocene Glacial Maximum, 1991-1994 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Encyclopedia of Appalachia, 2003-2006 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Molluscs and marine terraces - publications, correspondence, notes, 1989-2012 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Notes and figures including Quaternary sea-level changes on rising tectonic coasts: ice ages as reviewed from the South Pacific, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Quaternary sea-level fluctuations in the Pacific, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - High precision thorium-230 dating of corals using thermal ionization mass spectrometry: applications to paleoseismology, Undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Frozen assets of the ice cores: New Scientist, 1988-1988 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - A demonstration of stereophotogrammetry with combined SIR-B and Landsat TM images, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Coral Reefs, Island Arcs, and Ice Ages, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Karst morphology: Santo Island, Vanuatu, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Holocene Sea-level History and Tectonic Movements, Republic of Korea, 1985-1995 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - SIR-B Radar Imagery of Volcanic Deposits in the Andes, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Coastal terraces generated by sea-level change and tectonic uplift, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - The effect of the Patagonian ice sheet on relative sea levels along the Atlantic coast of South America: A numerical calculation, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Coseismic and Quaternary Vertical Tectonic Movements, Santo and Malekula Islands, New Hebrides Island Arc, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Late Quaternary Uplift History from Emerged Reef Terraces on Santo and Malekula Islands, Central New Hebrides Island Arc, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - The Sea-Level Record of the Structure of an Ice Age, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Earth Rheology, Isostacy and Eustacy, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Grooves on Phobos: Their Distribution, Morphology and Possible Origin, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Unused photos, 1928-1961 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Publications concerning Argentina, 1983-1989 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Journal of Geological Education volume 38, 1990-09 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Publications concerning Connecticut, 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - A large drop in Atmospheric 14C/12C and Reduced Melting in the Younger Dryas, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Japanese publications, 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Encyclopedia of Earth Sciences, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Oxford Companion, 1998-2000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Water Sciences - Macmillan, 2000-2002 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Journal and news publications, 1987-2003 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Publications concerning Papua New Guinea and Barbados, 1990-2003 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Publications concerning the Peruvian Andes, 1989-2006 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Encyclopedia of Appalachia, 1999-2006 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series III. Career, Public Outreach, Personal
  - Correspondence and career, 1965-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Maine, May 10-12, 1996, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Fall 1997 - Syracuse lecture, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Cornell Association of Professors Emeriti (CAPE), 2006-05 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Student outreach, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Cornell's Adult University (CAU) Folder 1, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Cornell's Adult University (CAU) Folder 2, 1989-1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Contains fossil fastened with tape to foil and paper "award" for Dr. Bloom; personal correspondence; poem by Eleanor Kleinhaus; newspaper clippings; photos
  - Cornell's Adult University (CAU) Folder 3, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Cornell's Adult University (CAU) Folder 4, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Cornell's Adult University (CAU) - Folder 5; future overseas trip, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Community courses and correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Senior citizen field trips, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Senior citizens local geology, 1998-03-03-1998-03-24 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Cornell talks, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Community and university volunteering Folder 1, 2001-2005 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Community and university volunteering Folder 2, 2005-2009 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "Fan mail", 2011-2013 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Career reports and materials; public outreach, 1961-1995 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Retirement and correspondence, 1994-1999 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Travel 1990-1991, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Travel 1991-1992, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Travel, etc. 1992-1993, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Travel, etc. 1993-1994, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Travel, etc. 1994-1995, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Series IV. Geology administrative documents
  - Cornell Geology program information, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Department meeting notes and correspondence - folder II, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Department meeting notes and correspondence - folder II, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1971, 1973, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 41)